Renee Chelian Papers RL.11808
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Renee Chelian Papers
1981-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Chelian, Renee, 1951-
RL.11808
6 Linear Feet 5 boxes
Renee Chelian founded the Northland Family Planning Center, a women's healthcare and abortion clinic in the Detroit area. The Renee Chelian papers include professional papers related to the Northland Family Planning Center, including materials related to anti-abortion groups picketing the clinic, as well as materials related to Chelian's involvement with national women's healthcare organizations.
Content Description
The Renee Chelian papers include professional papers related to Chelian's clinic, Northland Family Planning in Detroit, Michigan, and her work with national organizations including the American Civil Liberties Union and the National Organization for Women. Materials relate mostly to her work at the Northland Family Planning clinic during the 1990s and include newspaper clippings, photographs, pro-choice and anti-abortion materials, completed surveys from patients, family, and friends who visited the clincs, and administrative documents related to escort training, office supplies, and staff information.
The collection also contains materials, such as hate mail and pamphlets, related to anti-abortion groups and their picketing of the Northland Family clinic. Folders titled Saturday contain photographs of the picketors and picketing information of the anti-abortion protesting at the clinic. Materials also relate to other anti-abortion materials, including papers related to the harassment of other abortion providers and the murder of Dr. David Gunn, and anti-clinic organizations such as Operation Rescue, Life Dynamics, Prolife Action League, Feminists for Life, crisis pregnancy centers and leaders such as Randall Terry and Joe Scheidler.
Also included are materials from other women's health organizations and campaigns, including Stand Up For Women, Project Choice, and Operation Rescue. Some of the anti-abortion materials contain explicit images.
Biographical / Historical
Renee Chelian, born in 1951, has worked to provide safe abortions and healthcare for women. She began her career by assisting a physician performing abortions pre-Roe vs. Wade. In 1976, she founded Northland Family Planning Center in the Detroit area. Chelian is also a political activist, committed to local and national campaigns to preserve women's reproductive and civil rights. She has been honored by the National Organization for Women (NOW), the National Association of Women Business Owners, and the Michigan Women's Political Caucus for her professional and political contributions.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains VHS tapes that need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Renee Chelian papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2014.
Abortion -- United States; Abortion -- Political aspects; Abortion -- Press coverage -- United States; Abortion -- Law and legislation; Abortion -- Moral and ethical aspects; Abortion services -- United States; Abortion services -- Employees; Women in medicine; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Chelian, Renee, 1951-; Northland Family Planning Center
- American Family Planning Abortion Mill (Box 1)
- Saturday Christmas Rescue, 1986 December 2 (Box 1)
- Map and Land Of Clinic (Box 1)
- Press Conference re: Pope (Box 1)
- Pledge a Picket (Box 1)
- Pro Life Action Newsletter and Threat Newsletter (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1987 (Box 1)
- Lawsuit and Injunction (Box 1)
- Pope: Catholic Pro Life groups in Detroit, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
- Papal Visit, 1987 (Box 1)
- Michigan Catholic (Box 1)
- NOF Meeting on Pope visit - my workshop, May 1988 (Box 1)
- NP articles Pope visit (Box 1)
- Miami (Box 1)
- MOH Meetings re: pope visit (Box 1)
- Pope visit - survey, September 1987 (Box 1)
- Pope vist - Lawsuit Southfield (SFD), September 1987 (Box 1)
- Escant - Northland Family Planning (NFP) (illegible) (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue: Northland Family Planning (NFP) Plan (Box 1)
- Picketing, 1990 April 26 (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue Northland Family Planning (NFP)/National Organization for Women (NOW) (Box 1)
- Legal actions and demonstrations (Box 1)
- Locks (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue: Prouder Meeting re: OR, 1989 February 27 (Box 1)
- Meeting PPL, National Organization for Women (NOW), American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), (illegible) etc. (Box 1)
- Other requests (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue: Costs/ results and attrests, etc. (Box 1)
- Women's clinic - press release, 1987 (Box 1)
- Newsletters: re: operation rescue press release (Box 1)
- Ann Baker Operation Rescue Kit (Box 1)
- Scottsdale Medical, 1987 October 7 (Box 1)
- Womancare Lathrup, 30 September 1989 (Box 1)
- Picketing re: O.R., June 9-10 (Box 1)
- Saturday: Northland Family Planning (NFP) West, 1989 July 1 (Box 1)
- P.C.C. Lavinia Womanscare, 1987 April 29 (Box 1)
- Good Friday Womanscare, 1989 March 24 (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue woman scare Sterling Height, 1989 February 25 (Box 1)
- August 1989 (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue East Gyn Articles, 1989 January 21 (Box 1)
- Operation Rescue, 1988 November 12 (Box 1)
- Right To Life Crusade (Box 1)
- 1988 November 12 (Box 1)
- Refuse and Resist, 1989 (Box 1)
- 6 January 1990 (Box 1)
- Escort Training (Box 1)
- Escort Newsletter, 1990 (Box 1)
- Escort Report Form (Box 1)
- CDAR (Box 1)
- National Organization for Women (NOW) Volunteers (Box 1)
- NWROC (Box 1)
- June 1989 (Box 1)
- 1989 July 8 (Box 1)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) - West newsletter, November-December 1990 (Box 1)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) - West picket file, January-April 1991 (Box 1)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) - West Picketers, May 1991 - December 1991 (Box 1)
- Jan. 1992 to June 1992 (Box 1)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) - West, July 1992 - May 1994 (Box 1)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) - West, April - June 1990 (Box 1)
- Life Dynamics, 1993 (Box 2)
- Project Choice (Box 2)
- Frestown (Box 2)
- Book/Kit to Lawyers (Box 2)
- Life Dynamics: Bottom Feeder (Box 2)
- Dr. David Gunn, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
- Dr. Seller Slat, August 1993 (Box 2)
- Dr. David Gunn: Frend (Box 2)
- Dr. David Gunn: Newspaper (Box 2)
- Dr. David Gunn: Dr. David Gunn's murder, 1993 March 10 (Box 2)
- Dr. David Gunn: Dr. Gunn/M. Griffin trial, March 1994 (Box 2)
- Operation Rescue: Witchita Kansas, August 1991 (Box 2)
- Buffalo, 20 April 1992 - 4 May 1992 (Box 2)
- Missionaries to the Preborn: Bootcamp, 1993 (Box 2)
- Missionaries to the Preborn: Early Pregnancy (Box 2)
- Missionaries to the Preborn, 1994 (Box 2)
- Harassment: Wanted Protestors, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Harassment: Fetus of Refuge, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Harassment: Jeri Rassmusen, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- PPL: response to Dr. Brittons (Box 2)
- Madam US Battle Zone: ND Article, 1994 (Box 2)
- Battle Zone, 1991 (Box 2)
- Materials related to anti-abortion, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
- PWB Case (Box 2)
- Press Releases (Box 2)
- Ypsi Womancare Lok n' Blok, 1991 November 12 (Box 2)
- American Front Plan, November 9 (Box 2)
- Frend Womancare, 30 October 1991 (Box 2)
- East n' Blok, 26 October 1991 (Box 2)
- Real Witchita, 19 October 1991 (Box 2)
- Womancare, August 1991 (Box 2)
- Good Frend Nat Day of Res, January - March 1991 (Box 2)
- Toledo Lok n' Blok, 19 October 1991 (Box 2)
- Center for Choice correspondence, 1987 (Box 2)
- Toledo, 29 September 1989 (Box 2)
- September 30 - October 7 1989 (Box 2)
- Kalamazoo (Box 2)
- Grand Rapids, Michigan, 1989 (Box 2)
- Bower and Chervenka letter, 1988 (Box 2)
- Hate mail to Lyn Riegle, 1989 (Box 2)
- Grand Rapids Women's Health (Box 2)
- Washthenaw, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
- Operation Rescue: articles, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
- Rescue Update, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
- Operation Rescue: Detroit Anti-Abortion Literature, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
- Operation Rescue: Chester alerts, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
- Operation Rescue, 1981-1992 (Box 2)
- Operation Rescue: Laura Justine (Box 2)
- Feminists for Life of America, 1993 (Box 2)
- Anti abortion related to Operation Rescue staff (Box 2)
- Pro-Life Action League: Meeting, 16 February 1990 (Box 2)
- Pro-Life Action League: General Sidewalk Counseling (Box 2)
- Pro-Life Action League: American Rights Coalition (Box 2)
- Home Picketing, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
- Home Picketing: City Ordinance (Box 2)
- Home Picketing: Mighican Criminal Law (Box 2)
- Home Picketing: Brochure home address (Box 2)
- Home Picketing: Anti mailing, 17 March 1990 (Box 2)
- Home Picketing, 2 June 1990 (Box 2)
- Home Picketing, 21 March 1991 (Box 2)
- Home Picketing, 22 February 1992 (Box 2)
- Home Picketing, 30 October 1994 (Box 2)
- Home Picketing: NP articles (Box 2)
- Legal documents about anti-abortion protestors, 1990; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Defense Action, 1994 (Box 2)
- Meeting re: home picket (Box 2)
- Health Care Clinic Pontiac, 10 November 1990 (Box 2)
- 2 June 1990 (Box 3)
- Mother's Day legal picket, 12 May 1990 (Box 3)
  General
  [Sat.]
- Denise Erin Jones (Box 3)
- Operation Rescue picket, 24 February 1990 (Box 3)
- Dr. Jacob Kalo case (Box 3)
- West (Box 3)
- West picketing (Box 3)
- Hate mail/picketing (Box 3)
- Ante articles at East (Box 3)
- 9:10 am-1:00pm Saturday, 14 July (Box 3)
- 8:45 left 11:00 Saturday, 28 July (Box 3)
- 8:30 - 12:00 Saturday, 21 July (Box 3)
- Saturday, 4 August (Box 3)
- 16 August (Box 3)
- 18 August (Box 3)
- 25 August 1984 (Box 3)
- 1 September 1984 (Box 3)
- 8 September 1984 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 22 September 1984 (Box 3)
- 9:30 / 11:00 Saturday, 13 October 1984 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 8 December 1984 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 15 December 1984 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 22 December 1984 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 29 December 1984 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 5 January 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 12 January 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 19 January 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 17 January 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 2 February 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 9 February 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 16 February 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 2 March 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 9 March 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 16 March 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 23 March 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 30 March 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 6 April 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 13 April 1985; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Friday at West, 19 April 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 20 April 1985 (Box 3)
- Friday at West, 26 April 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 4 May 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 25 May 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 8 June 1985 (Box 3)
- Saturday, 15 June 1985 (Box 3)
- 29 June - 17 July 1985 (Box 3)
- 31 August 1985 (Box 3)
- Correspondence with Bureau of Alcohol, Firearms, and Tobacco, 4 August 1987 (Box 3)
- Larry Walworth correspondence, 26 September 1987 (Box 3)
- Jesus Bag, undated (Box 3)
- West, September - October 1989 (Box 3)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) picketing, July - September 1990 (Box 3)
- Life Dynamics, 1993-1998 (Box 3)
- Clinic violence - Denying the Right to Choose (Box 3)
- Clinic violence: clinic picketing - Northland Family Planning (NFP) (illegible) forms (Box 3)
- Life Dynamics and Abortion Malpractice, circa 1990s (Box 3)
- United States Marshall visit, 5 November 1995 (Box 3)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) - Southfield (SFLD), 1991-1993 (Box 3)
- Picketing at Northland Family Planning (NFP) - Southfield, July-December 1990 (Box 3)
- Picketing at Northland Family Planning (NFP) - Southfield, January-June 1990 (Box 3)
- Southfield (SFLD), September-November 1989 (Box 3)
- Picketing at Northland Family Planning (NFP) - Southfield, 27 July 1989 (Box 3)
- Articles on Ricco (Box 3)
- Ricco info (Box 3)
- John Salre / Brookline Massachusetts (Box 3)
- Home picketing (Box 3)
- Anti literature (Box 3)
- Shari Richard, 1991 (Box 3)
- Project Stand Up for Women National Organization for Women (NOW), 1990 (Box 3)
- Anti-abortion materials, 1985-1995 (Box 3)
- Lambs of Christ (Box 3)
- Anti-abortion protestors, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Northland Family Planning (NFP) West, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Project Truth, 1995 (Box 4)
- Clinic violence and protestors for and against abortion rights, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
- Dr. Plan (Box 4)
- Ricco (Box 4)
- HB4618 Access Bill, 1993 (Box 4)
- Michigan HB 5499, 1990 (Box 4)
- Pro-choice materials, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
- Injunction against Operation Rescue, 1989 (Box 4)
- Civil action against Operation Rescue, 1989 (Box 4)
- Lynn Mills, 1993 (Box 4)
- Clippings about Operation Rescue, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
- Joseph Scheilder, 1985-1990 (Box 4)
- Other anti-abortionists/terrorists (Box 4)
- Other anti-abortionists/terrorists: Carol Everett, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
- Anti-Abortion Terrorist Want Ad, 1988 (Box 5)
- Monaghan and Domino's Pizza Boycotting, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
- American Civil Liberties Union, 1989 (Box 5)
- Operation Rescue News Clippings, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
- Picketing Events, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
- Allentown Women's Center, 1993 (Box 5)
- Kids Picketing, 1993 (Box 5)